Register of the Vitaliĭ Leonidovich Kataev papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vitaliĭ Leonidovich Kataev papers
1966-2001
2002C48
Hoover Institution Archives
20 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize folder (8.4 linear feet)
The papers of Vitaliĭ Leonidovich Kataev, Russian engineer, Soviet defense industry official, and adviser to President Mikhail Gorbachev, include reports, memoranda, correspondence, diaries, notes, meeting and conference materials, electronic documents, and sound recordings relating to Soviet military policy, the Soviet defense industry, Soviet nuclear weapons, and Soviet participation in arms limitation negotiations.
Kataev, Vitaliĭ Leonidovich, 1932-2001.
Access
Box 15 is closed; use copies of materials are available in the Hoover Archives reading room. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To access any video recordings or motion picture material, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1932 October 29 Born, Perm, Russia
1956 Graduated from the Kazan Aviation Institute, Russia
1956-1960 Aviation system designer, senior engineer, Ministry of Aviation Industry, Omsk Aviation Factory, Russia
1960-1974 Leading designer, Senior Engineer Group, specialist on engine system of missiles (strategic missile complexes SS-7, SS-9, SS-17, SS-24, and space complex "Interkosmos"), Ministry of General Engineering, Dnepropetrovsk Southern Factory, Ukraine
1974-1990 Instructor, head of sector, deputy head of department, curator for creation and production of strategic submarine-launched missile complexes (SS-H-17, SS-H-18, SS-H-20, SS-H-23), CPSU Central Committee, Department of Defense Industry Production, Moscow, Russia Organizer and member of the Interdepartmental Working Group ("Group of Five")
1990-1992 Deputy head of the Department for State Defense and Security, part of the apparatus of the president of the USSR
1992 First deputy to the chief of the State Council of the Russian Federation for converting military industry; prepared material for establishing a security council Director-general, Business Center, military-industrial complex
1997-2001 Research fellow, Institute of Mechanical Engineering, Russian Academy of Science, Moscow; held copyrights and patents on classified subjects
2001 September Died, Moscow
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection documents the activities of Vitaliĭ Kataev, who worked as deputy head of defense and security on the staff of the President of the Soviet Union, Mikhail Gorbachev. Kataev took a direct part in negotiations on the reduction and limitation of strategic offensive weapons, conventional armed forces in Europe, space weapons, and the destruction of chemical weapons. He also worked on limiting underground testing of nuclear weapons, the non-proliferation of missiles and missile technology, the prevention of dangerous military activities, and the mutual reduction of armed forces on the Soviet-Chinese border, as well as other defense topics. He covered military and technical cooperation with foreign countries, particularly the supply of arms and military equipment. Kataev was also an aviation systems designer and chief designer of projects for strategic ground-based missile complexes and sea-based strategic missiles.
Materials in the collection include documents from the period of the Cold War and early post-Cold War period; computer discs with working materials from the Cold War period and new technology draft projects; and sound cassettes of interviews of participants in the Cold War from the Soviet military industrial complex (VPK).
Documents from the period of the Cold War and early post-Cold War period include materials related to the review of problems in USSR military policy, the preparation of CPSU Central Committee resolutions on military-political issues and issues in Soviet-American relations, and problems of national security and stability of relations. Additionally, there are retrospective (beginning from the 1960s) and organizational documents related to the structure of the higher units of analytical work and preparation of reports regarding military-political problems, directives to Soviet delegations involved in negotiations with the West (excluding the withdrawal of troops from Warsaw Pact countries), as well as related to the more important problems in the work of the Interdepartmental Working Group – Piaterka (Group of Five) and of the Commission of the Politburo – the higher or Big Piaterka.
Papers include scientific-technical, military-technical, and military-political materials for delegations negotiating for the liquidation of intermediate range missiles (INF negotiations), limiting and reducing strategic missiles, space weapons and SDI/ABM, "Open Skies," non-proliferation of missiles and missile technology, and the cessation of nuclear testing. The collection contains extensive material on the liquidation of chemical and biological weapons, the reduction of conventional arms and armed forces in Europe (CFE), and armed forces along the Soviet-Chinese border. There are also documents on confidence-building measures and open territories, summit meetings, and military-technical cooperation with Warsaw Pact countries and other countries, as well as materials which characterize the relationship between individual military political leaders of the USSR and these issues.
Diaries beginning from 1974 include Kataev's notes made during work in the CPSU Central Committee Defense Industry Department, in the apparat of the Defense and Security Department of the USSR President (Gorbachev), and as a state advisor of the Russian Federation on conversion. The diaries include the analysis of technical and organizational problems, descriptions of types of technology, and tables indicating test results. They also contain transcripts of local meetings on technology, of the Head Constructors Councils, of the leadership of the IUzhnoe defense plant in Dnepropetrovsk, and of the CPSU Central Committee and other organs.
Soviet Union--Military policy.; Soviet Union--Defenses.; Nuclear weapons.; Arms control.; Engineers.; Audiotapes.
- Biographical File, 1966-1999 (Boxes 1-3)
  - Contents of the personal archive of Vitaliĭ Leonidovich Kataev, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes listing of electronic files.
  - Diaries (handwritten in notebooks)
    Include the results of analysis of technical and organizational problems, descriptions of types of technology, tables indicating test results, and transcripts of local meetings of the leadership of the IUzhnoe defense plant in Dnepropetrovsk, the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU) Central Committee, and other organizations.
    - Work problems of IUzhnoe designer bureau on creation a new technology; advice of general designers, orders, resolutions, participants of work, 1966-1972 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Research on work in creation of compound systems in missile technology, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Interview with participants in the Cold War, 1993
    - Notes on the work in IUzhnoe designer bureau regarding creation of a new technology, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Work in IUzhnoe designer bureau and military industrial complex (VPK), 1974-1984, 1997
    - Notes on the problems of creating a new technology, 1974-1989 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Notes on work of defense factories involved in creating a new technology; designer bureau work, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Notes on the problems of elaborating a new technology, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Working notes on the problems of creating a new technology (designer Makeev V. P.), 1982-1983 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Notes on the work of party committees of the defense factories and designer bureaus; creation of a new technology, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Notes on the work of the Ministry of General Mechanical Engineering and other ministries and on the work of designer bureaus and defense factories working on the problems of new technology, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Notes on the work of defense factories and designer bureaus; secretariat of the CPSU Central Committee on preparation of the 28th Congress of the CPSU; meeting before disintegration of the Soviet Union (1991 August 8); conversion, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Notes on the problems of military politics and reduction of armaments; "Piaterka" work, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 2: 5)
      "Piaterka" is 1. Defense Ministry, 2. Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 3. KGB (Committee of State Security), 4. Council of Ministers (Commission on Military-Industrial Questions) and 5. CPSU Central Committee (Defense and Foreign Relations Departments). All together there were about 30-40 people present at the meetings.
    - Notes on the problems of military technical cooperation, meetings in the office of the Politburo of the CPSU Central Committee member Lev Zaikov, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Work notes on problems in negotiations and creating a new technology, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Notes on the problems discussed at Zaikov's meetings, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Notes on the problems of reduction of armaments, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Notes on "Business-Center VPK (military-industrial complex)" work, 1992-1994
    - Notes on problems resolved by Interdepartmental Work Group "Piaterka,", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Daily notes, 1991 March - December (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Daily notes, 1991 July 21-27 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Daily notes, 1991 December 6 - 1992 April 30 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Notes on work in Eltsyn's apparatus (service of the State Counsellor on conversion), 1992 May 5 - December 21 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Daily notes, 1993 November 5 - 1994 February 16 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Daily notes, 1993 December 1 - 1994 April 21 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Minutes of a discussion by 25 ex-leaders of the Soviet Union on the question of disintegration of the Soviet Union, 1999 June 21 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Correspondence with A. A. Kokoshin, deputy director of the Institute of the United States and Canada of the Academy of Science of the Soviet Union, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 3: 12)
- Correspondence and Reports of Mikhail Gorbachev, 1986-1991 (Box 4)
  Correspondence, considerations, declarations, directives, evaluations, excerpts from meetings, initiatives, inquiries, instructions, official letters, lists, notes, orders, recommendations, reference material, reports, resolutions, speeches, statements, suggestions, summaries, and transcripts (stenograms) relating to negotiations between the Soviet Union and the United States and other countries regarding nuclear weapons, arranged chronologically.
  - Letter to George Bush from Mikhail Gorbachev (?), unsigned, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Draft letter to George Bush from Mikhail Gorbachev (?), unsigned, undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Report of the status of the situation in negotiations on the nuclear space armaments, unsigned, undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Draft material for negotiations with James Baker, Secretary of State of the United States, unsigned, undated (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Considerations regarding intermediate-range offensive weapons for meeting with James Baker, unsigned, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Directions for the meeting between E. Shevardnadze, Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union with Ronald Reagan, unsigned, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - 1986
    - Possible suggestions of the Soviet Union on the question of joint moratorium on nuclear weapons testing between the Soviet Union and the United States, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Statement of Mikhail Gorbachev, January 15 (Box-folder 4: 8)
      "Suggestions of the Soviet Union on the Program of Total Liquidation of Nuclear Weapons All Over the World by the Year 2000" ("Predlozhenie SSSR o programme polnoi likvidatsii iadernogo oruzhiia vo vsem mire k 2000 godu"). Document presented as a chart by S. F. Akhromeev.
    - Letter to Mikhail Gorbachev from E. Shevardnadze, A. Dobrynin, and A. IAkovlev regarding use of outer space for peaceful purposes, July 21 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - Correspondence and resolution regarding contacts of military representatives of the Soviet Union and Federal Republic of Germany on the questions of security and disarmament, July-August (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Thoughts for meeting with Ronald Reagan, October (Box-folder 4: 11)
      Includes resolution of the CPSU Central Committee on possible positions for the meeting in Reykjavik.
    - Major issues for the meetings of the General Secretary of the CPSU Central Committee Mikhail Gorbachev with Ronald Reagan on the question of nuclear disarmament, October (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Reference material to major positions for the meetings of the General Secretary CPSU Central Committee with the President of the United States in Reykjavik, October 11-12 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Directives, protocol, and resolution in negotiations with the United States on the question of establishing centers for reducing nuclear danger (Peregovory po sozdaniiu tsentrov po umen'sheniiu iadernoi opasnosti), November 21 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - Evaluation of the military-political situation, December 18 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - 1987
    - Statement of Mikhail Gorbachev regarding the program of gradual liquidation of nuclear weapons, February 28 (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - Working material from General S. Akhromeev to the CPCU Central Committee regarding a new Soviet military-political initiative regarding a nuclear-free corridor in central Europe, March (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - 1988
    - Instructions for the meeting of the Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union in Washington, February 17 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - Directives for negotiations with George Shultz, Secretary of State of the United States, March 20-23 (Box-folder 4: 19)
      Includes preliminary draft of the joint Soviet-American declaration on chemical weapons ban (for adoption at the summit meeting).
    - Directives for negotiations with George Shultz, April 18 (Box-folder 4: 20)
      Includes resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, Moscow, 1988 February 21-23.
    - Draft note of the CPSU Central Committee about steps for prevention of redeployment of American aircraft from Spain to other European NATO countries, May 25 (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - Draft of the CPSU Central Committee for the Soviet-American summit meeting in Moscow, May 23 (Box-folder 4: 22)
      Includes resolution of the CPSU Central Committee.
    - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, June 23 (Box-folder 4: 23)
      "Declaration on Reduction of Military Forces and Armaments in the Central and Southern Part of Europe" ("O vystuplenii s initsiativoi o sokrashchenii voisk i vooruzhenii v TSentral'noi chasti i na IUge Evropy"). Includes thesis for the speech of the General Secretary of the CPSU Central Committee in the Polish Parliament.
    - Directives of the CPSU Central Committee for negotiations with American leaders in Washington and ministers of foreign affairs of a number of foreign countries in New York, September 20 (Box-folder 4: 24)
    - Summary of meeting with G. Stauffer, Department of State expert on the Soviet Union, December 9 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - 1989
    Material related to the meeting at the highest level in Europe between Mikhail Gorbachev and George Bush, Malta, 1989 December 2-4.
    - Correspondence regarding thoughts on the content of negotiations between Mikhail Gorbachev and George Bush on military-political issues, November 23 (Box-folder 4: 26)
    - Preliminary list of questions for the meeting with George Bush (Box-folder 4: 27)
    - Position preparedness order of the Soviet Union on military-political questions based on the results of the Malta meeting (Box-folder 4: 28)
      Includes list of problems based on the results of the Malta meeting.
    - Resolution of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union on the results of the Soviet-American meeting, December 2-3 (Box-folder 4: 29)
      "Po itogam sovetsko-amerikanskoi vstrechi na vysshem urovne 2-3 dekabria 1989 goda na Mal'te." Includes list of problems based on the results of the meeting on Malta.
    - Initiatives of George Bush proposed during Malta meeting (Box-folder 4: 30)
    - Material on the question of new Soviet initiatives in the area of reduction of armaments (Box-folder 4: 31)
    - Press conference of George Bush, Brussels, December 4 (Box-folder 4: 32)
  - 1990
    - Inquiry to negotiations on intermediate-range offensive weapons, February (Box-folder 4: 33)
      Includes resolution of the CPSU Central Committee regarding approach on counting of air-launched cruise missiles (ALCM) in negotiations on nuclear and space weaponry.
    - Suggestions on the issue of naval forces for the meeting of E. Shevardnadze with James A. Baker, January (Box-folder 4: 34)
    - Official letter to Eduard Shevardnaze from James A. Baker, February 3 (Box-folder 4: 35)
      Includes draft memorandum of understanding regarding destruction of chemical weapons.
    - Summary of meeting with James Baker, February 7-8 (Box-folder 4: 36)
    - Transcript (stenogram) of meeting with James Baker, April 20 (Box-folder 4: 37)
    - Excerpts from the meeting between James Baker and Mikhail Gorbachev, May 11 (Box-folder 4: 38)
    - Joint (USSR-USA) declaration regarding future negotiations on nuclear and space armament and further strengthening of strategic stability, Washington, June 1 (Box-folder 4: 39)
    - Joint (USSR-USA) declaration regarding START Treaty, Washington, June 1 (Box-folder 4: 40)
    - Suggestions from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union for meeting with James A. Baker, June 12 (Box-folder 4: 41)
    - Draft order of the President of the Soviet Union, July (Box-folder 4: 42)
      "Suggestions on Remaining Unsolved Questions in Negotiations on Nuclear and Space Weapons, on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe, and on the 'Open Skies' Conference" ("O predlozheniiakh po ostaiushchimsia nereshennym voprosam na peregovorakh po iadernym i kosmicheskim vooruzheniiam, po obychnym vooruzhennym silam v Evrope i Konferentsii po "otkrytomu nebu'), compiled by Lev Zaikov, V. Kriuchkov, E. Shevardnadze, A. Iakovlev, I. Belousov, and M. Moiseev. Includes the order of Mikhail Gorbachev.
    - Considerations on military-political questions (disarmament), for the meeting between E. Shevardnadze and James Baker, July 7 (Box-folder 4: 43)
    - Letter to Mikhail Gorbachev from the Director of the Defense Department of the CPSU Central Committee O. Beliakov and Director of the State Legal Department of the CPSU Central Committee A. Pavlov, July 26 (Box-folder 4: 44)
      "On the Change of Order of the Solution Adoption in Some Questions in Defense Building" ("Ob izmenenii poriadka priniatiia reshenii po nekotorym voprosam oboronnogo stroitel'stva").
    - Official letter to James A. Baker from Eduard Shevardnadze regarding agreement on intermediate-range missiles, July 28 (Box-folder 4: 45)
    - Notes from meeting with Eleanor Sutter, First Secretary of the Embassy of the United States in Moscow, August 2 and 7 (Box-folder 4: 46)
    - Draft of future negotiations on nuclear and space armament and strategic stability to Mikhail Gorbachev from Lev Zaikov, V. Kriuchkov, E. Shevardnadze, D. Iazov, and I. Belousov, August 30 (Box-folder 4: 47)
    - Notes from meeting with Jack Matlock, Ambassador of the United States to the Soviet Union, September 3 (Box-folder 4: 48)
    - Official letter to Mikhail Gorbachev from George Bush, regarding the CFE (Conventional Forces in Europe) and START (Strategic Arms Reduction Talks) treaties, September 17 (Box-folder 4: 49)
    - Report from Eduard Shevardnadze to Mikhail Gorbachev about urgent measures regarding completion of work on the treaty on conventional armed forces in Europe (CFE) and the treaty on reduction and restraining of strategic offensive armaments, September 18 (Box-folder 4: 50)
    - Considerations of the Soviet leaders on the question of START agreement for the meeting of the ministers of foreign affairs of the Soviet Union and the United States of America, New York, September 26 (Box-folder 4: 51)
      Includes declaration of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics regarding the intermediate-range bomber Tu-22M.
    - Official letter from James A. Baker to Eduard Shevardnadze, October 3 (Box-folder 4: 52)
      Typescript, in English with Russian translation.
    - Report to Mikhail Gorbachev from E. Shevardnadze, October 10 (Box-folder 4: 53)
      "About Results of the Negotiations in New-York, 1990, September 22-October 5" ("Ob itogakh peregovorov v N'iu Yorke 22 sentiabria - 5 oktiabria 1990 goda").
  - 1991
    - Official letter from E. Shevardnadze to James A. Baker, January (Box-folder 4: 54)
    - Transcript of conversation between E. Shevardnadze and Jack Matlock, January 7 (Box-folder 4: 55)
    - Speech of the Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs A. A. Obukhov on the meeting of the Commission of the Central Committee of the Soviet Union, February 1 (Box-folder 4: 56)
    - Address to Mikhail Gorbachev from The Right Honorable Sir John Major, Prime Minister of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, April 5 (Box-folder 4: 57)
      Includes addition on the Soviet program in the area of biological war.
    - Secret message from George Bush to Mikhail Gorbachev, June 5 (Box-folder 4: 58)
    - Official letter to George Bush from Mikhail Gorbachev regarding acceleration of work on the strategic offensive armaments treaty, June 13 (Box-folder 4: 59)
    - Suggestions for meeting in Berlin (1991 June 21) between A. A. Bessmertnykh, Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union, and James A. Baker on the question of strategic offensive armaments treaty (Box-folder 4: 60)
    - Recommendations to Mikhail Gorbachev from Lev Zaikov, O. Baklanov, A. Bessmertnykh, V. Kriuchkov, V. Masliukov, and D. IAzov for the Soviet-American meeting on the highest level in Moscow (1991 July) on the questions of reduction of armaments and disarmament, July 11-12 (Box-folder 4: 61)
      "O soobrazheniiakh po voprosam ogranicheniia vooruzhenii i razoruzheniia k vozmozhnoi sovetsko-amerikanskoi vstreche v verkhakh v Moskve."
- Arms Control File, 1975-1999 (Boxes 5-11)
  Analytical information, assessment of different agreements, charts, considerations on possible resolutions, data, declarations, directives, facts, inquiries, lists, maps, minutes of meetings, notes from meetings, proposals, progress reports, protocols, requests, resolutions, statements, speeches, studies, suggestions, summaries, tables of strategic nuclear weapons, talking points, texts of declarations, thesis for discussion, and miscellaneous material regarding strategic weapons and strategic command control, arranged by the type of negotiations and chronologically thereunder.
  - Documents regarding US-Soviet relations, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Strategic Arms Reduction Talks (START), 1982-1992
    - Strategic stability and further reduction of the strategic offensive weapons, undated (Box-folder 5: 2)